(English Subtitle) Growing.Pains.S01E11 -= Standardized.Test =- Subripped by zerox
如入无人之境 这家伙真的势不可挡
And he's tearing up the board, folks. This man cannot be stopped.
凯罗，把看家本领拿出来吧 我准备好了，血气翻腾
All right, give me your best shot here, Carol. I feel hot. I feel ready.
好
Okay.
帕梅拉.邓肯纳德 理查德.加兰德主演的.
What 1957 Roger Corman film...
1957年罗杰.考曼的什么电影？
starred Pamela Duncan and Richard Garland?
你真的要问？
What, are they serious?
，来点难度好吗？
Attack of the Crab Monsters. Come on, give me a hard question, Carol.
真不可思议
I don't believe it.
凯罗，记得这歌吗？
Oh, wow, Carol, remember this song?
记得，我们小时候爸妈经常听
Yeah. Mom and Dad used to play this to us all the time when we we're little.
记得我们以前会怎样吗？
Yeah, remember what we used to do?
这不是遗传的吧？
I hope this isn't hereditary.
同胞们，成绩单游戏
Hey, guys, report cards came.
-成绩单游戏？ -这是你的
- Oh, yeah? Our report cards came? - Yeah. This is yours.
我们有个孩子喜欢成绩单
Maggie, we have a child who actually likes getting report cards.
我们到底做错了什么？
Where did we go wrong?
我知道成绩，但还是很紧张
I don't know why I'm so nervous. I mean, I already know what I got.
对了，优，优，优，优..!
Yep. A, A, A, A, A, A!
-太棒了，麦克 -太好了
- That's great, sweetie. Mike.... - Good for you.
中，中，中，中.
C, C, C, C...
差，良
D, B.
起码有一科良
Well, he did get one B.
-体育？ -对了
- Phys Ed. ? - You got it.
-让我受不了的是.. -我知道，他很聪明
- What drives me crazy is that-- - I know, he's not dumb.
二年级时他都能得到良和优良
In first and second grade, he got Bs and B-pluses.
直到凯罗出现，全部拿优
Well, that was before Carol came along and started getting all As.
-真有种 -是啊
- The nerve. - Yeah.
至少他风光了两年
Well, at least he had two great years.
比几百年前的人好多了
That's better than that poor guy a couple of popes ago.
杰森
Jason.
你也许要求太高了
Maggie, maybe we're being a little too hard on him, you know?
不是所有孩子都能拿优
Not all kids have to get As.
但是最近几年每况愈下
But for the last couple of years it's been getting worse.
这是青春期惹的祸
Well, that's what puberty's for.
碰到困难就认为穷途末路
You take a difficult situation and you make it impossible.
-麦克，去哪了？ -我去找杜克
- Where you been, Mike? - Oh, I thought I'd go look for Duke.
-麦克，杜克6个月前就走丢了 -啊？
- Mike, Duke ran away six months ago. - So?
而且不是我们的狗
And he wasn't our dog.
“我们的狗”是什么意思？
What does that really mean, Dad? "Our dog."
人有权利去拥有另一种生物吗？
I mean, can one person ever really own another living thing?
-我上楼去 -我看这样吧
- Maybe I should go look upstairs. - Hey, I got a great idea.
大家看看信对里面有什么
Why don't we all take a look at what's in this envelope?
好吧
Oh, okay.
“麦克.西弗，恭喜赢得2百万奖金”
"If your name is Mike Seaver, you may have already won $2 million."
妈妈，生气前请注意.
Hey, look, Mom, before you get too upset...
某些分数是有可能打错的
you should know that some of these grades might be wrong.
我们害怕的是有些打对了
What scares us is some of them might be right.
我得到中，并不差，中等
Hey, I got a C average. That's not bad, it's average.
你就是想得到中等？
Is that what you want to be, Mike? Average?
其实比中等高一点
Well, it's a high C, so actually it's a little above average.
-良好到中等之间？ -也没有那么高
- Don't they have C-pluses for that? - Well, it's not that high.
你可以拿更高分的
You can do better than this, can't you?
这不是我的错.
It's not my fault, Mom, I just....
我和老师有冲突
I have a personality conflict with my teacher.
麦克，6科6个不同的老师.
Mike, you have about the same grades...
你拿到的成绩都一样
in six different subjects with six different teachers.
我知道
I know.
我不喜欢的人都喜欢去当老师
The profession just seems to attract people who are difficult to get along with.
我们还要说多少遍？
Mike, how many times do we have to go through this?
你需要努力一点
I mean, you're just going to have to work a little harder.
我很努力了
I am working hard.
为什么我每次上楼.
Then why is it every time I go up to your room...
你应该在房间里学习时.
when you're supposed to be studying...
我却看到你睡觉，掷飞镖
you're either napping or throwing darts?
我需要轻松一下
That's how I unwind.
麦克.
Mike.
你已经尽力了？
Look, Mike, are you saying that you're trying as hard as you can?
是的
Yeah.
这些“中等”就是你的最高水平？
So these Cs are honestly the best you can do?
我可以超过“中等”的
No, I can get better than Cs, Dad.
几何这科怎么得差了？
Well, Mike, what about this D in geometry?
不知道
I don't know.
课程太难了？
Are the classes too hard for you?
你需要选容易一点的数学课吗？
I mean, would you rather be in a math section that's a little less demanding?
爸爸，我有能力的 我不是及格了吗？
Dad, I can do it. Look, I'm passing, aren't l?
别让我跟傻瓜一起上课
Like, you don't have to go putting me in with the rejects.
凯克，还玩吗？
Hey, Mike, want to finish our game?
不打扰你欣赏“优秀”成绩单了
No, I wouldn't want to keep you from admiring your As.
-继续吧，不妨碍你 -拜托
- Please, go ahead. Don't let me stop you. - Come on, Mike.
别谦虚，一起分享这个时刻
Oh, don't be modest, Carol. Come on, let's share this special moment.
凯罗，真让人骄傲
Oh, I'm so proud of you, Carol.
代数：优! 社会科：优!
Algebra : A! Social Studies: A!
-书呆子科：特优! -我不是书呆子
- Advanced Nerdiness: A+! - I'm not a nerd.
书呆子也没什么不好
Hey, Carol, there's nothing wrong with being a nerd.
没有书呆子 还有谁去买学校的东西？
I mean, without nerds, who would buy all the back-to-school supplies?
还有谁去约会数学队的人？
Who would date the guys on the math team?
还有谁上课时举手？
And who would raise their hand in class and go, "Ooh, ooh"?
你得不到好成绩，所以妒忌我
Well, you're just jealous because you never get good grades.
若是我肯学习，我会拿优的
Look, if I studied, I could probably get all As.
若是有吃饭课，你也拿不到优秀
You couldn't get an A in Lunch as a Second Language.
真有意思，凯罗 有考虑过当相声演员吗？
Oh, that's funny, Carol. Have you ever considered being a standup?
可以谈化学喜剧
Maybe you could do, like, chemistry comedy and stuff.
你真是个混蛋
You are such a jerk.
可以拿好成绩，干嘛不去学习？
I mean, if you could get such good grades, then why don't you study?
因为我还有更重要的事
Because I have better things to do.
例如呢？ 让罗依德的鼻孔喷牛奶？
Like what? Like getting Lloyd Kreeger to laugh milk out of his nose?
不，例如跟朋友一起玩 某些人连朋友都没有
No. Like hanging out with friends, which certain people don't have.
好吧.
Yeah, well....
周一看看谁更聪明？
We'll just see how smart you are on Monday, won't we?
周一怎么了？
Why, what's Monday?
全校参加爱达荷智力测试
It's the day the whole school takes the Idaho Standardized Test.
我若是温习一下 或许拿全校最高分
So? If I study, I'll probably get the highest grade in school.
笨蛋，这种测试是无法温习的
You can't study for this test, bonebrain.
这是智力测试
It's an aptitude test.
我知道
I know.
什么是智力测试？
What's an aptitude test?
就是IQ测试，看看人有多聪明
It's basically an IQ test. To see how smart you are.
在你的角度，是测试你有多愚蠢
Or, in your case, how smart you aren't.
听好了，这是爱达荷智力测试
All right, now, listen up. This is the Idaho Standardized Test.
我讨厌测验，讨厌这种铅笔
God, I hate these tests. I hate number two pencils.
讨厌这种经历
I hate this whole experience.
冷静点，没什么大不了
Hey, look, calm down, will you? This isn't such a big deal.
没什么大不了？
Not a big.... Not a big deal?
我大腿上的豆豆都冒汗了
Tell that to the hives that are breaking out on my thighs.
你大腿上长豆豆了？
You get hives on your thighs?
-要看看吗？ -不了，我相信你
- You want to see them? - No, I believe you.
天哪
Oh, my God.
这些测试不算进成绩单
This test doesn't even count on your grades.
测验结果有何关系？
I mean, what difference does it make what you get?
开玩笑，这是IQ测试
Are you kidding? This is an IQ test.
比成绩重要10倍
This is 10 times more important than your grades.
等等，你在说什么？
Wait. What are you talking about?
这测试能判断我们有多聪明
This test decides once and for all how smart we are.
从今尔后 父母就会知道我们多笨
I mean, after today, our parents will know how stupid we are.
兄弟姐妹就会知道我们多笨
Our brothers and sisters will know how stupid we are.
也许整个爱达荷州 也会知道我们有多笨
I can only assume the whole state of Idaho will know how stupid we are.
父母也会知道成绩？
Our parents get these results?
说起来就长了
I'll never hear the end of it.
“可怜的里奇，没有他哥哥戴维聪明”
"Poor Richie, he's just not as smart as his brother David.
“戴维今年要到普林斯顿大学念法学”
"Our David is pre-law at Princeton this year.
“里奇，倒垃圾去”
"Oh, hi, Richie, could you take out the garbage, please?
“也许以后这就是他的行业”
"We're hoping he can do it professionally someday."
你哥哥又怎样了？
Look, what do you care about your brother?
只是个书呆子 谁家里没有书呆子？
I mean, so he's a nerd. Every family's got a nerd.
对了，你也有凯罗
Hey, yeah, that's right. You got Carol.
她是个天才
She's a genius.
你站在她旁边就像一头猪
You're gonna look like a tree stump next to her.
才不是
No, I'm not.
其一，我和她是一样聪明的
Because for one thing, I am just as smart as she is.
其二，我不相信这种测试
And for another thing, I happen not to believe in these tests.
瞧我干什么？我连题目都不看
I mean, you know what I do? I don't even read the questions.
我在答卡上画图，这样
I just fill in these computer dots in a pretty pattern, like this.
考试开始
All right. You may begin.
你疯了，干什么？
What? You're crazy. What are you doing?
这是自画像 爱达荷州的人也喜欢这个
Oh, it's a self-portrait. They'll love this in Idaho.
埃维斯先生
All right, Mr. Ellis...
今天结束前还有什么要说吗？
is there anything else you'd like to talk about before we stop for today?
-没有了，一切都很好 -好
- Nope. Everything's just great. - Good.
你的问题大大改善了
Okay. Well, I think we're making some real progress here with your problem.
我有什么问题？
What problem's that?
你有习来惯性撒谎的问题
Well, Mr. Ellis, we both know, don't we, that you're an habitual liar?
没有
No, I'm not.
-埃维斯先生.. -好吧
- Mr. Ellis.... - Okay, okay.
别逼问我
Don't pressure me like this.
我的人生要完了
My whole life is going down the drain.
一分钟前你还说“一切很好”
But, now, just a minute ago, you said, "Everything is just great."
没有
No, I didn't.
这.
Well, then...
我们下次要好好聊聊
we certainly do have a lot to talk about next time, Mr. Ellis.
下次？我再也不回来
What next time? I'm never coming back here again.
-随便你 -好吧
- Whatever you say. - Fine.
-下周一见 -好的
- See you next Wednesday? - Good. Yeah.
本，来吧
All right, Ben. et's do it.
-爸爸 -本
- Dad.... - Come on, Ben.
我没有要求你做过什么 希望你不要推搪
I don't ask you to do too much around here. When I do, I expect it to get done.
-爸爸，但是.. -不得异议
- But, Dad-- - Without an argument.
晚点行不行？
Can't I do it later?
-本，别惹我 -好吧
- Ben, you're testing me, now. - All right.
这才像样
That's more like it.
-本，真是颗天生的星星 -什么意思？
- Ben, you're a born Pip. - What's a Pip?
一种精神境界
A state of mind.
喂？
Hello?
等等，找你的
Okay, wait one second. It's for you.
别走，还没完
Don't go away, now. We're not done.
喂
Hello.
我老婆不在家
Well, no, my wife is at work.
对，当然了，既然那么重要
Yes.... Yes, of course, if it's important.
好吧，到时候见
All right, I'll see you then.
本，关掉音乐
Hey, Ben, will you turn that off, please?
喂，麦姬
Yeah, Maggie?
半小时后能赶到学校吗？
Can you meet me down at the high school in about a half an hour?
学校的心理医师，关于麦克
Well, it's the school psychologist. It's about Mike.
西弗先生太太，我们非常关心.
Dr. and Mrs. Seaver, we have some concern over....
薄荷糖？不要？
Breath mint? No.
-..麦克的IQ测试 -什么成绩？
- Over the results of Mikes IQ test. - Why? What did he get?
麦姬，这种测试很主观
Now, Maggie, you know, these are highly subjective.
许多医师甚至不考虑.
Many diagnosticians, they don't even consider these to mean....
-他的成绩多少？ -他的分数是.
- What did he get? - He got....
我先告诉你分数的含义
Well, let me just put this in context for you, Mrs. Seaver.
100分是中等，120是非常聪明.
Now, a score of 100 is about average, 120 is very bright...
140是天才，160是.
140 is considered a genius, 160 is--
-麦克得到多少？ -27分
- What did Mike get? - A 27.
什么？荒谬，明显搞错了
What? This is ridiculous. I mean, this is obviously a mistake.
对不起，西弗太太 我们已经反复校对
I'm sorry, Mrs. Seaver. We've checked and double-checked.
-木糖醇？ -不要了
- Antacid? - No.
27分？
Twenty-seven?
你是心理医生那就好了
I'm glad that you're a psychiatrist, Dr. Seaver.
你明白我的意思吗？
You'll understand what I'm saying here.
你说我的儿子是傻瓜
Yeah, you're saying my son is an idiot.
不，严格来说是低能
No, technically, he's an imbecile.
什么？
What?
1至25是傻瓜，25至50是低能
Well, 0 to 25 is an idiot. 25 to 50 is an imbecile.
那我们就放心了
Well, that's certainly a load off my mind.
60到70是白痴
et's see, I believe that 60 to 70 is a moron.
50到60是什么？
No, wait. What's 50 to 60?
不知道，头大无脑？
I don't know. A bozo?
不
No!
算了，这个跟麦克没有关系
Never mind. This has nothing to do with Mike.
对，根据测试结果.
No. Because according to this...
麦克距离头大无脑还很遥远呢
Mike could never even aspire to become a bozo.
西弗先生太太，我们不能反应过度
Now, Dr. and Mrs. Seaver, the worst thing we can do is to overreact to this.
麦克最近有撞到头部吗？
Has Mike taken a sharp blow to the head recently?
没有
No.
有过长的缺氧吗？
Suffered any prolonged oxygen deprivation?
我儿子没有大脑损伤
No, Dr. Marlens, our son is not brain-damaged.
好吧，只是确保万一
Okay. Just checking.
麦克的档案说明.
Now look, Mike's file indicates he's always had a....
他有叛逆性
Well, how shall we say, a problem with authority.
例如这里写的去年.
For example, it says here that last year...
他把小老鼠.
he placed a litter of baby gerbils...
放到布赖来恩老师的面巾盒里
into Mrs. O'Brien's Kleenex box...
接着她用面巾擦鼻子
and when she went to blow her nose....
那老家伙真的.
That old bag must have just....
不好意思
Excuse me.
我只是寓工作于娱乐 这里还有很多好东西
There's so little joy in my job, and he's got a lot of good stuff in here.
谢谢
Thank you.
你的意思是？
Dr. Marlens, what are you getting at?
瞧这个
You see this?
这是正常的答卡，很凌乱
This is a normal test answer sheet. It's a mess.
答案随机分布在页面上，瞧这个
The little dots are scattered randomly around the page. You see this?
你儿子的答卡
This is your son's test answer sheet.
在画面上构成图形，有房子，飞机.
The dots make up little pictures of houses, airplanes.
瞧这里，是个女性的身体
Look here, there's even one of a young woman's body in profile.
好身材
Nice figure.
你是说麦克是故意的
So, you're saying.... You're saying that Mike did this intentionally.
要不然麦克就是个 有艺术才华的低能儿
Well, either that, Mrs. Seaver, or he's a highly artistic imbecile.
弹什么？很好听
What is it? That's pretty.
没什么
Nothing.
听说今天你见家长了
Well, I heard you got called down to the school psychologist today.
是的，爸妈现在学校
Oh, yeah. Mom and Dad are down there right now.
是吗？你做些什么了？
They are? Why? What'd you do?
我IQ测试拿了27分
Well, I got a 27 on my IQ test.
爸妈不会在乎这种测试的.
Mom and Dad really don't care about that sort of thing, so, you know...
别难过.
don't feel bad.
你拿到27分？
You got a 27?
笨蛋，我是故意的
Yeah, I did it on purpose, bonehead.
-我甚至没有看题目 -什么？
- I mean, I didn't even read the questions. - What?
我知道自己聪明 为什么浪费宝贵的时间.
I mean, I know I'm brilliant, so I figured, why waste my valuable time...
去玩填字游戏？
on playing fill-in-the-dots?
不是吧
Come on, you didn't really do that.
凯罗，怎么说呢
Carol, how should I put this?
在你出生前，爸妈曾对我说.
You see before you we're born, Mom and Dad came to me and they said:
“麦克，我们希望下一个孩子能读书”
"Mike, we hope that our next child isn't some goody-goody nerdface...
“要像你一样，能独立思考”
"but that he's a real independent, free-thinker, like you."
是的
Yeah.
他们不知道你的智力达到了峰值
Little did they know, you had peaked intellectually.
麦克.
Mike?
他们会打死你的
They're gonna kill you.
也许他们发现这种测试的无聊后.
Carol, maybe Mom and Dad have realized how stupid these tests are.
他们会敬仰我的做法
Maybe they're gonna admire me for what I did.
麦克，可以说两句吗？
Mike. Could we speak to you for a moment, please?
他们要正式地打死你
Maybe they're gonna have you killed professionally.
麦克，请解释这是什么？
Mike, can you explain to us what this is?
好吧
Oh, okay.
这是波音747，这是大鲈鱼.
This here is a Boeing 747, and this is a largemouth bass...
这是罗来恩达的肖像
and this.... This is a full-body profile of Rhonda Tishkin.
麦克，为什么这样做？
Mike, why did you do this?
她身材很好
She's got a great body, Mom.
这可不是说笑，为什么这样做？
Mike, this isn't a joke. Come on, why did you do that?
不知道，我就喜欢这样
I don't know. I just felt like it.
喜欢这样？
You just felt like it.
我不知道你们如此在乎这些测试
Well, gee, I didn't realize how important these tests we're to you guys.
你们应该早告诉我.
Maybe you should have told me that you we're only interested...
我们只在乎高IQ的孩子
in having kids with high IQ scores.
麦克
Mike.
没关系 你们已经有一个聪明的孩子
Hey, that's okay. I mean, you guys got one smart kid.
“优秀”女士也许能成为宇航员.
Miss Straight As here can go and become an astronaut...
麦克打杂就好了，没关系
and Mikey can always mix the Tang, no problem.
让他冷静一下吧
Why don't we just let him cool off?
-好吧？ -好吧
- Okay. - Okay?
干什么？
What do you want?
没什么，我.
Nothing, really, I mean, I just--
走开
Then why don't you just get out of here?
麦克，你并不笨
Look, Mike. You're not really stupid.
谢谢你，凯罗 我感到你的光芒了
Well, thanks, Carol. I am deeply touched by your superiority.
麦克，别感到愚蠢
I hope I don't make you feel stupid, Mike.
那你走开就好了
You don't make me feel stupid. Just get out of here, okay?
没有人感到愚蠢，因为我不愚蠢
Nobody makes me feel stupid, "cause I'm not stupid.
我不是这样说了吗？
I just said that.
也许我因为愚蠢，听不懂
Well, maybe I was just too stupid to understand.
麦克，拜托.
Mike, come on. I mean...
你老是说我是书呆子.
you're always calling me a nerd and stuff...
我当时只是想报复你
and I don't know, I guess I was just trying to get you back.
因为你更成熟，更酷
I guess "cause you're older, and cooler and everything.
我就觉得.
And I just figured that...
只有我一个人难过
I was the only one who was getting hurt.
我是个书呆子.
I mean, I am sort of a nerd...
但你不蠢
but you're not really stupid.
你得“优秀”，我得“中等” 这是巧合吗？
Oh, so, I guess it's just coincidence that you get all the As and I get all the Cs?
我也不知道为什么你成绩不好
Look, I don't know why you don't get good grades. I mean....
或许是因为.
Well, maybe it has something to do with the fact...
你在做功课时睡觉，掷飞镖
that you sleep and play darts while doing your homework.
飞镖有什么不好？
What is it with the darts?
这里没有人懂得放松了吗？
I mean, am I the only guy around here that knows how to unwind?
听好了.
Okay, listen.
麦克斯.怀来恩伯格什么时候.. 替布鲁斯.斯普林斯丁打鼓伴奏？
What year did Max Weinberg start playing drums for Bruce Springsteen?
怎么撇开话题了？
Hey, did we just start a new conversation?
说吧，什么时候？
Come on, what year?
1973年，什么意思？
1973. So what does that mean?
意思是麦克斯.怀来恩伯格的收入 会激增.
Well, aside from being a huge boost in income for Max Weinberg...
还有你很聪明
it means you're pretty smart.
因为记住了这种没用的事情？
What, cause I know one useless fact?
你记住了数不清的没用的事情
You know millions of useless facts.
例如什么
I mean, like the Attack of the Crab People thing.
-真的难以相信 -是
- I mean, I couldn't believe that. - Crab Monsters, Carol.
Attack of the Crab Monsters.
你记不住考试的内容
See, I mean, you don't remember things for tests.
因为某种原因.
You just remember things you want to remember...
你只记住想记住的事情
for some strange reason.
记性好算什么
So I have a good memory. Big deal.
还不止呢.
It's more than just that. I mean.... Okay.
记得情人节你借了我20块吗？
Remember last year when you borrowed $20 from me on Valentines Day?
是的
Yeah. So?
-我让你写借据 -我乐意写
- And I made you sign an IOU? - Which I gladly did.
你说2月29日还我
Promising to pay me back on February 29th.
到了1988年我会还你
Hey, come 1988, that $20 is yours.
那做法不但很聪明.
You see, that, that wasn't just intelligent...
而且很有创造性
that was actually very creative.
不，是你笨而已
No, you we're just a sucker.
这就是我的意思
You see, that's my point. I mean...
我经常做傻事
I do dumb things all the time.
你喜欢时就会做聪明的事
And you do smart things when you feel like it.
-这.. -但是.
- Well.... - But, hey.
妈妈不是经常骂你别自作聪明吗？
Why do you think Moms always telling you to shut your smart mouth?
要做到这般讨厌 还是需要一定的智力和努力的
I mean, it takes brains and hard work to be as obnoxious as you are.
是的
Yeah, I guess it does.
喜欢做的事情谈不上努力
But when you love what you do, it really doesn't seem like work.
去他的，也许我们的IQ一样呢
I mean, heck, for all we know, you and I might have the same IQ.
是啊，也许我比你高呢
Yeah, who knows? Mine might even be higher.
别歇斯底里了
et's not get hysterical, now.
-凯罗 -嗯？
- Hey, Carol? - Yeah?
谢谢
Thanks.
-你这混蛋 -书呆子
- You jerk. - Nerd.
我是善意的
I meant that in a nice way.
谢谢你，非常感谢
Oh, good, thank you. Yes, thank you very much.
好吧，再见
All right. Bye-bye.
老师说你可以再来一次 爱达荷智力测试
Hey, Mike, Dr. Marlens says you can take that Idaho Test over again...
周六早上10点
Saturday morning, 10:00.
爸爸，太好了 只不过.
Oh, that's great, Dad, but....
我很满意27分这个分数
Well, I've been thinking about it and I'm kind of happy with the 27.
-麦克 -好吧，10点
- Mike. - Yes, Dad. Okay, 10:00.
[zeroxia@gmail.com] 2006.03.12